Women's Action Alliance Records, 1970-1996
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- SERIES II. PROJECTS 1972-96, 63.75 linear ft.
  Records of the Women's Centers Project (WCP) are arranged in six sections: Administration, Surveys, the National Association of Women's Centers, Women's Rights Lobby Day, the Women's Centers and AIDS Project, and the Job Training Partnership Act and Women's Centers Project. The Administration and Surveys sections document how the WAA sought to identify and analyze the multi-service women's center, which was in the 1970s an emerging form of community-based social-service delivery agency. Preliminary data was gathered in 1978, which brought together the staff of five exemplary centers: the Women's Center for Education and Career Advancement (New York, NY), a project of the National Council of Negro Women; the Lesbian Resource Center (Seattle, WA); WomenSpace (Cleveland, OH); the Midwest Women's Center (Chicago, IL); and the Everywoman's Center (Amherst, MA). In 1980, the WCP took a broader survey of women's centers across the U.S. in which they conducted site visits and interviews and mailed questionnaires. Among the WCP's results were two publications: an annotated directory of multi-issue women's centers, and a detailed report on the women clients who used and preferred the services women's centers provide.
  This work spearheaded the creation of the National Association of Women's Centers (NAWC), established in May 1986 to strengthen women's centers, provide technical assistance to them, and advocate on their behalf. The records document the series of conferences that were held to launch the organization.
  The Women's Center's Project additionally hosted independent initiatives. The 1987-88 Job-Training Partnership Act and Women's Centers Project (JTPA) analyzed the effectiveness of the JTPA in reaching women's centers by fifteen women's centers across the nation. Jo Sanders's Staying Poor: How the JTPA Fails Women (Metuchen: Scarecrow Press, 1988) was the result of this survey. The Women's Centers and AIDS Project, which is documented primarily by funding proposals and reports, generated two publications: Women's Centers and AIDS Project: A Guide to Educational Material (1988) and Women, AIDS, and Communities: A Guide for Action (1991), The Women's Rights Lobby Day project contains planning material and publicity for a lobbying effort that took place on 4 February 1981.
- SERIES III. RESOURCES 1970-96, 15 linear ft.
  In addition to the projects the WAA supported, one of the organization's main functions was to act as an information clearinghouse, though the form this aspect of the organization took underwent several changes over the years. Only a few months after the WAA's formation, it was receiving some 200 letters per week from women seeking advice and information. In response to those inquiries, the WAA launched its Information and Referral Services. Much of this mail came from women across the country "who want to know about existing women's organizations in their area, or who want to find a local woman professional - a sympathetic lawyer, doctor, psychiatrist, etc. - to help with a particular problem." In response, the WAA initiated a directory and referral service. Over time, this arm of the WAA would grow to include a large library, a publications program, and other referral services. The series is divided into three subseries: Information and Referral Services, Library, and Publications.
  Information and Referral Services
  Records pertaining to the WAA's Information and Referral Services are arranged in three sections that reflect the development of this information-clearinghouse function of the organization over time: Project SHARE, Technical Assistance Program, and Reference Services.
  The first incarnation of the WAA's informational clearinghouse was Project SHARE, which supplied "support, hook-up, research and education" assistance. SHARE's three areas of activity included information collection, maintenance, and dissemination; materials development; and technical assistance training. In response to numerous requests from women and women's centers throughout the country, in 1973 Project SHARE published How to Organize a Multi-Service Women's Center. The records of Project SHARE are primarily administrative. Materials from How to Organize a Multi-Service Women's Center are located in SERIES III. RESOURCES-Publications.
  In 1977-78, SHARE evolved into the Technical Assistance Program (TAP). TAP was formed to provide information, referrals, and consultation services to women's organizations planning new projects. The Library took over the general duties of collecting information. Technical Assistance programs and projects focused on assisting women and women's organizations in one or more of seven areas; fundraising, management, legal assistance, program planning and development, outreach, and community and political action. Eventually, the WAA decided to publish such information in a directory format, embarking on the Technical Assistance Directory Project.
  The Technical Assistance Program records are arranged into three parts: Administration, Directory Project, and Proposal Critique Service. The Administration section includes fundraising materials and surveys. Directory Project records include surveys and responses in addition to the administrative records of the technical assistance directory.
  The Proposal Critique Service was undertaken by the Women's Action Alliance in cooperation with Women & Foundations/Corporate Philanthropy (WAF/CP). Its mission was to "encourage organized philanthropy to support programs for women." The service provided technical assistance in proposal writing to individuals and organizations seeking corporate, governmental, and foundation funding. Upon receipt, proposals were either critiqued by a member of the WAA Technical Assistance staff or referred to a member of Women in Foundations/Corporate Philanthropy whose area of expertise was relevant to the proposal's subject. The program began in January 1979 and was discontinued in December 1980 due to volunteers' inability to provide their services in a timely enough fashion.
  Proposal Critique Service records are comprised of administrative material, including such materials as general history, program descriptions, promotional information, and submitted proposals with critiques. The administrative records, especially the surveys, logs and requests, reflect the WAA's efforts to address the needs of women and women's organizations in the late 1970s. The proposals themselves are organized into subject areas.
  A fourth section of the Information and Referral Services subseries is devoted to Reference Services. Collected here are the inquiries fielded by the Information and Referral Services program. In many ways, this is the genesis of the whole WAA project; inquiries include the early letters sent to Gloria Steinem and Ms. magazine that prompted the founding of the WAA. This section includes incoming and outgoing reference correspondence, whether directed to Project SHARE or one of its successors. Reference correspondence was filed by subject and that arrangement has been retained. A particularly interesting set of letters, filed under "Health" and "Obstetric/Gynecology," date from circa 1973 after an article in Ms. invited readers to share their own childbirth experiences (some of this correspondence is also filed under "Health."). The subject-oriented filing system broke down in the mid-1970s, and though some effort has been made to file subsequent inquiries by subject, a large amount of mail remains arranged chronologically in the "General" file.
  Library
  This subseries is arranged in two sections: Administration, and Reference collections. Administrative materials include documents illuminating collection development. A small amount of material relates to the Women's Information Services Network, and the Women Helping Women Database Project, an effort to create a computerized companion to the publication of the same name (see Publications). The majority of the WAA's Reference collections, e.g. the many books, magazines, newsletters, journals, and most of their vertical files, were not acquired with the organization's records; materials preserved here, however, include numerous topical bibliographies, handouts, and reading lists collected and developed by the WAA. Two sets of card files containing contact information for agencies and organizations are each filed by subject. The two sets appear very similar in organization and purpose, but have been retained, in their original order, as separate systems; researchers interested in a particular topic should check both.
  Also housed here are subject files originally collected by Catherine Samuels and a set of vertical files, organized by state, with information gathered on women's centers. Finally, the New York City Referral System was created for internal purposes in 1977 to enable the WAA to refer local women to services in the metropolitan area.
  Publications
  This subseries contains booklets and books published and distributed by the WAA (by contrast, publications produced by individual WAA initiatives, e.g. Struggling Through Tight Times: A Handbook for Women's and other Non-Profit Organizations, produced by the Economic Development Project, are found with the records of that initiative). Most publications of the WAA were created by the Information Services program, which directed the Library and Information and Referral Services following the dissolution of the Technical Assistance Program. In response to a broad audience's previously unmet requests for assistance, staff created and revised resource lists designed to assist in responding to common requests. How to Organize a Multi-Service Women's Center was designed to answer requests for technical assistance from women's centers across the country. Getting your Share was written in 1976 to advise in the areas of fundraising and grant writing.
  The 1973 Women's Action Alliance Directory was an early attempt to develop a directory of national women's organizations that could provide basic information on women's issues, an effort that would see several incarnations over the ensuing decade. A larger and more formal publication, A Practical Guide to the Women's Movement, was completed in 1975. A revised edition, A (More) Practical Guide to the Women's Movement, appeared in 1978. Another edition, renamed the Women's Action Almanac, was published in 1980. Women Helping Women: A State-by-State Directory of Service appeared in 1981.
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS, 2.5 linear ft.
  This series includes primarily photographs from WAA events; photographs of WAA staff members are interspersed throughout. Photographs of WAA Events include Lynn Scherr, Marcia Ann Gillespie, Lily Tomlin, Gloria Steinem, and Wendy Wasserstein, as well as the subjects of the annual Women's Roasts: Geraldine Ferraro, Liz Smith, Donna Shalala, and Pat Schroeder. A set of portraits associated with an unidentified project includes Gloria Steinem, Selena, and Brenda Feigen Fasteau. Also housed here are photographs taken in connection with the various programs run by the WAA, including the Women and Work Expositions, the Non-Sexist Childhood Development project, "The Body Alliance: A Wellness Day for Women," the Resource Mothers project, and other efforts by the Women's Alcohol and Drug Project. Photographs associated with the Women's Centers Project include those taken at the Everywoman's Center (Amherst, MA) and the New Haven Women's Liberation Center Technical Assistance Workshops from 1980.
  The photographs related to the Non-Sexist Child Development Project consist of "resource photographs" developed by the project as teaching tools. These include photos of "Men in the Nurturing Role," photos of disabled children and adults, and images of men and women at work in occupations that challenge stereotypical sex roles. There are also photographs of the dolls developed by the Non-Sexist Child Development Project and distributed by Milton Bradley.
- SERIES V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIAL, 3 linear ft.
  This series includes mainly audiotapes, the bulk of which are associated with the Non-Sexist Child Development Project. The majority of these tapes were only partially labeled when they arrived at the Sophia Smith Collection. Some effort was made during processing to determine which WAA program or subprogram a given tape was associated with, but more research in the papers would probably enable a researcher to identify the specific event recorded. There are also audiotaped interviews from the Children of Single Parents in the Schools Project (1988).
  Among the audiovisual materials are several videotapes, most notably one surveying the Alliance in 1976, and one other, from the 1990s, surveying the WADEP project Listen to Us/Escuchemos. Finally, a number of computer disks were accessioned with the papers, including more than two dozen 5.25 in. floppy disks formatted for an early Apple computer. Where possible, files from computer diskettes were printed on contemporary printers; the bulk of this material was related to the Women's Alcohol and Drug Education Project. Some early WAA files, however, created in obsolete formats, remain inaccessible; the extent to which these electronic records are represented by paper copies is at present unknown.
  [Originals restricted - copies must be made for research use.]
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION 1971-96
  - General
    - Articles of Incorporation and other founding documents (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Certificate of change to the Articles, 1993-94 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - By-laws, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Calendar of annual events, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Fact sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Form letters, circa 1972, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Guidelines for Project Development, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Legal: correspondence and tax forms, 1974-80 (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
    - Letters of support following funding cuts, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Mission statement, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Organizational flow chart, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      [see also OVERSIZE]
    - Organizational reviews and evaluations, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Organizational reviews and evaluations, 1978-83, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
    - Program activities summaries and reports, 1980-88 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Reports and associated draft material, 1975-86 (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
    - Reports and associated draft material, 1975-86 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - State and regional affiliates: notes, proposals, correspondence and reports, 1972-77 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - U.S. Census of Service Industries, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors
    - General
      - Board of Advisors (forerunner of Board of Directors): lists, notes, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Board management: booklets, instructional packets, reports, 1975-94 (Box 3, Folder 8-11)
      - Elections: ballots and slates, 1976-83 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
      - Notebook (board reference), circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Policy on Ethical Conduct, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Reports prepared by staff and E.D. for board, 1973-77 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
    - Chairs
      - Gloria Steinem (1971-1978): correspondence, clippings, and transcript of Donohue show, 1971-89 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
      - Joan Shigekawa (1978-?): correspondence, biographicalinformation, press releases, 1979-89, undated (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
      - Catherine Samuels (?-?)
        - Correspondence, 1974-93 (Box 5, Folder 1)
        - General (includes fundraising work), 1976-82 (Box 5, Folder 2)
        - American Revolution Bicentennial Administration: correspondence, reports, meeting materials, miscellany, 1973-76 (Box 5, Folder 3-9)
        - Subjects
          - Boston Women's Municipal Employment Project: correspondence and papers, 1971-72 (Box 5, Folder 10)
          - C-M (includes Consciousness-raising materials and Samuels' 1974 paper "The Evolution of the Women's Movement, 1971-74") (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
          - N-Z (includes Stewardesses for Equal Rights and the Women's Prisons Project, 1972-73) (Box 6, Folder 5-15)
      - Kay Ellen Consolver (?-1997): correspondence and miscellany, 1989-93, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Committees: minutes, agendas, memoranda, notes, correspondence
      - General: assignments and reply cards, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
      - Ad-Hoc, on Board Development, 1981-86 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Agenda, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Benefit, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Committee on Directors, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Corporate Advisory 1978 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Decentralization, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Development/Fundraising, 1974-79 (Box 7, Folder 11-18)
      - Directors, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - Economic Development Project, 1982-85
        - General, 1982, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
        - Minutes and memoranda, 1982-84 (Box 8, Folder 1)
        - Proposal materials, 1982-83, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Executive Committee, 1973-86 (Box 8, Folder 3-11)
      - Finance, 1983-84 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Men for the ERA, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Nominating, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Operations Review Task Force, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Personnel, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Programs, 1983-84 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Project Share, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Search, 1979, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Membership
      - General: lists, addresses, attendance records, board development and biographical material, 1973-94 (Box 12, Folder 9-12)
      - "Information Compiled on Prospective Board Members," undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Individuals: includes bio sheets, correspondence, notes, etc., 1974-89
        - B-F (includes Ivy Bottini, Coy Eckland, Brenda Feigen Fasteau, Mark Fasteau, and Martin Fischbein) (Box 13, Folder 2-15)
        - G-M (includes John Kenneth Galbraith, Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Marjorie Knowles, Marlene Krauss, Madeline Lee, and Maya Miller) (Box 13, Folder 16-30)
        - N-Shapiro (includes Eleanor Holmes Norton and Letty Cottin Pogrebin) (Box 13, Folder 31-40)
        - Simmons-Z (includes Franklin Thomas, Judith Thoyer, and Edith Van Horn) (Box 14, Folder 2-9)
    - Minutes, 1971-78 (Box 14, Folder 10-16)
    - Minutes, 1979-96 (includes also bound volume, 1975-80) 1974-89 (Box 15-18)
  - Executive Director
    - Correspondence (includes Brenda Feigen Fasteau, Helen Grace McCabe, and Marlene Krauss), 1970-96 (Box 19-21)
    - Subjects (arranged alphabetically)
      - A (Box 21, Folder 9-12)
      - B-C (includes the Boston Redevelopment Authority Sex Discrimination Project, Catholic Dialogue, and Coalition building) (Box 22, Folder 1-15)
      - C-M (includes Fundraising) (Box 23, Folder 1-17)
      - M-W (includes Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, White and Garrison) (Box 24, Folder 1-23)
      - W (includes the White House Conference on the Family) (Box 25, Folder 1-13)
    - Individuals
      - Ruth J. Abram 1974-79
        - Appointment books, 1978-79 (Box 26, Folder 1)
        - Biographical information, 1978 (Box 26, Folder 2)
        - Correspondence, 1974-79 (Box 26, Folder 3-8)
        - Correspondence, 1974-79 (Box 27, Folder 1-11)
        - Expenses, 1978-80, undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
        - Memoranda, 1974-80 (Box 28, Folder 2)
        - Miscellany, 1974, undated (Box 28, Folder 3)
        - Speech, Planned Parenthood, undated (Box 28, Folder 4)
        - Subjects
          - A-D (includes Bella Abzug) (Box 28, Folder 5-26)
          - D-H (includes material from Abram's service on the Domestic Policy Review on Industrial Innovation Public Interest subcommittee, U.S. Department of Commerce) (Box 29, Folder 1-18)
          - H-I (includes International Women's Project) (Box 30, Folder 1-14)
          - I-N (includes International Women's Year Commission) (Box 31, Folder 1-22)
          - National Council on Philanthropy (Box 32, Folder 1-14)
          - N-P (includes Public Interest Satellite Group) (Box 33, Folder 1-22)
          - P (Box 34, Folder 1-9)
          - P-V (Box 35, Folder 1-16)
          - V-W (includes Viva) (Box 36, Folder 1-17)
          - W-Z (includes Women's Yellow Pages, Working Woman) (Box 37, Folder 1-7)
      - Arlie Scott 1979-1982
        - Biographical information, 1980 (Box 38, Folder 1)
        - Conference attendance, 1980 (Box 38, Folder 2)
        - Correspondence 1980-82 (Box 38, Folder 3-5)
        - Letter of Agreement, 1982 (Box 38, Folder 6)
        - Notes for Executive Committee meetings, 1980 (Box 38, Folder 7)
        - Policy paper, undated (Box 38, Folder 8)
        - Subjects
          - Anti-busing amendment: memoranda, 1979 (Box 38, Folder 9)
          - Lamda Legal Defense and Education Fund (Box 38, Folder 10)
          - National Abortion Rights Action Week, 1979 (Box 38, Folder 11)
          - National Organization for Women (includes Fillmore v. Oklahoma Publishing Co.: correspondence and memoranda, 1979), 1979-81, undated (Box 38, Folder 12-15)
          - Political Campaign Institute, 1979 (Box 38, Folder 16)
          - Right to Life Convention, 1979 (Box 38, Folder 17)
      - Sylvia Kramer 1982-?
        - Biographical information (Box 39, Folder 1)
        - Letter of Agreement, 1983 (Box 39, Folder 2)
        - Coalition of the Concerned for Older Americans, 1983 (Box 39, Folder 3)
        - Conferences attended: fliers, 1982-83 (Box 39, Folder 4-5)
        - Correspondence, 1983-88, undated (Box 39, Folder 6-9)
        - Memoranda: general and Administrative Assistant Gerry Pearlberg, 1983-87 (Box 39, Folder 10-11)
        - Miscellany, 1979-84, undated (Box 39, Folder 12)
        - National Organization for Women (Box 39, Folder 13)
        - Notes, 1983 (Box 39, Folder 14)
        - Speeches
          - "On the Death of the Women's Movement," 1986 (Box 39, Folder 15)
          - "Women's History Celebration," 1986 (Box 39, Folder 16)
          - Research materials (Box 39, Folder 17)
        - New York City Chancellor's Advisory Commission to Promote Equality, 1980-84 (includes Task Force on Sex Equality material) (Box 40, Folder 1-6)
  - Publicity and Public Education
    - General: goals, reports, proposals, correspondence and miscellany (includes correspondence of Martha M. Jones, Director of Press and Communications, 1975-76), 1975-79, undated (Box 40, Folder 7-15)
    - Press coverage: clippings, 1972-80 (Box 40-41)
    - Promotion
      - Advertisements: rate information, directory listings, miscellany, 1979, undated (Box 41, Folder 4-11)
      - Press appearances: memoranda, 1980, undated (Box 41, Folder 12)
      - Press kit, National ERA march, 1978 (Box 41, Folder 13)
      - Press releases, 1972-82, undated (Box 41, Folder 14-15)
      - Promotion lists, 1978, undated (Box 41, Folder 16)
      - Public service announcements: correspondence, memoranda, invoices, and schedules, 1978-80, undated (Box 41, Folder 17-18)
      - Public service announcements: research materials and scripts, 1977-79, undated (Box 42, Folder 1-2)
      - Publications: brochures and newsletters (includes Viva magazine), 1978-88, n.d (Box 42, Folder 3-7)
      - Public Interest Public Relations (PIPR), Inc.: contracts, correspondence, media advisories, press releases, memoranda, and fact sheets, 1977-79 (Box 42, Folder 8-13)
  - Staff, 1976-83
    - General
      - Correspondence, 1972-76, 1987-88 (Box 42, Folder 14-15)
      - Feminist work groups, 1980 (Box 42, Folder 16)
      - Floorplans of office space, 1977, undated (Box 43, Folder 1)
      - Insurance (Box 43, Folder 2)
      - Miscellany (Box 43, Folder 3)
      - Staff lists, 1980-84, undated (Box 43, Folder 4)
      - Office space: notes and correspondence, 1976-77, undated (Box 43, Folder 5)